Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company Agreements 5489
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company Agreements
1914-1974
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company (C&O)
5489
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents), collective labor agreements.
Collective bargaining agreements of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company.
5657048
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, July 02, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, July 02, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company [CO] began as the Louisa Railroad in Louisa County Virginia in 1836. With the aid of the Commonwealth of Virginia, the railroad expanded to Richmond and Charlottesville, and eventually over the Blue Ridge Mountains and through the Shenandoah Valley. During this period, it was renamed the Virginia Central Railroad. During the Civil War, the CO was one of the Confederacy's most important assets, and was used both to move supplies to Richmond, the capital of the Confederacy, and to move troops and supplies into battle. As a result, the CO was heavily targeted by the Union Army and at the war's end was only left with roughly five miles of track in operation. Financially devastated, the CO turned to Collis P. Huntington of New York for capital investment. Huntington was one of the "Big Four," the men who had built the Central Pacific Railroad. With his financial aid, the CO stretched through West Virginia, accessing its coalmines, and reached the Ohio River in 1873. In 1878, the company was reorganized under the name Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. From 1878 to 1888, the CO capitalized on its coal assets and extended its reach to the new city of Newport News, in Hampton Roads, Virginia, the largest ice-free harbor on the east coast of the United States. In 1888, Huntington lost control of his interests in the CO to William K. Vanderbilt and J.P. Morgan.
During the first decades of the 20th Century, the CO capitalized on its access to the coalfields of West Virginia. In 1910, it took over the Chicago, Cincinnati, and Louisville railroad, giving the CO a direct line to Chicago. At this time, the CO also gained possession of the Hocking Valley line through Ohio, giving the road access to Columbus and the port of Toledo. In 1923, the CO came under the control of the Van Sweringen brothers, who also owned controlling interests in the Nickel Plate Road, the Pere Marquette Road and the Erie. Their control of these lines was lost during the Great Depression, but the CO itself remained strong and was one of the few roads that did not enter receivership. Rather, it used the economic circumstances to take advantage of cheap labor and materials to rebuild itself. This was in large part due to its continued hauling of coal, which remained in great demand. Because of these improvements, the CO was heavily utilized during World War 2, both to move materials and men to its port on the Hampton Roads, which was a point of embarkation for the United States Armed Forces heading to the European Theater.
In the post-war period, the CO was controlled by Robert R. Young. Under his stewardship, and then that of Walter J. Tuohy, the CO updated its locomotives and rolling stock, installed the first large computer system in railroading, and diversified its traffic by merging the Pere Marquette road into its system. The Pere Marquette's main traffic was to the numerous automotive industries in Michigan, which insulated the CO against the declining coal trade.
In 1963, the CO took financial control of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, which also brought the Western Maryland Railway under its umbrella. The merging of the systems was gradual, insulating the CO from potential pitfalls. By 1973, the three roads were fully integrated into one, The Chessie System, an old nickname for the CO dating back to the 1930s. In the final decades of the 20th Century, the CO continued to merge with other major systems in the southeastern United States, forming CSX Transportation. CSX is one of the seven Class 1 railroads currently operating in the United States.
(See Chesapeake and Ohio Historical Society, for more information)
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1914-1974
Bulk dates: 1914-1974
This collection consists of collective bargaining agreements between the CO, its predecessor, partner, and successor railroads with various labour organizations representing its various classes of employees. Because of the size and varied interests controlled by the CO, the agreements cover a wide swath of employees including everyhting from sleeping car Porters, to tug boat captains, to the "Big Four" railroad labor brotherhoods. Also found in this collection are agreement made by the United States Railroad Administration during the nationalization of the railroads during World War 1.
Also found in this collection are a series of "Yearbooks of Railroad Information," published by the Eastern Railroad Presidents' Conference and a successor organization, the Association of American Railroads.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Collective labor agreements -- Railroads; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions; Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company; Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company; Pere Marquette Railway; Staten Island Rapid Transit Company; Order of Railroad Telegraphers (U.S.); Railroad Yardmasters of America; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; National Maritime Union of America; Association of American Railroads; International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers, Roundhouse and Railway Shop Laborers; American Train Dispatchers' Association; Railway Shop Laborers; Brotherhood of Railway, Airline, and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, and Station Employes; Railway Patrolmen's International Union; United Transport Service Employees, Local 320; International Longshoremen's Association, Local 1768; National Organization, Masters, Mates and Pilots; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Switchmen's Union of North America; United States Railroad Administration
5657048
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Agreements, 1940-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Agreement, 1967; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Employees on Its Lake Michigan Car Ferries represented by National Maritime Union of America
    Format: Pamphlet.
  - Item 2: Agreement, 1974; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Its Employees in the Craft of Conductors, Assistant Conductors and Trainmen represented by the United Transportation Union on the Southern and Western Regions (Excluding Hocking Division). No.1
  - Item 3: Agreement, 1958; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Pere Marquette District and Employees Represented by the Order of Railroad Telegraphers and applying to similar employees of the Fort Street Union Depot Company and the Union Belt of Detroit
  - Item 4: Agreement, 1949; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company Pere Marquette District and the Lake Michigan Car Ferry Employees represented by the National Maritime Union of America
  - Item 5: Rules Governing Rates of Pay and Working Conditions, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Agreement Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Train Porters represented by the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters
  - Item 6: Supplementary Agreements, Interpretations, and Letters, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Agreed to between the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees and the following railroads: Chesapeake and Ohio Railway; Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad; Virginian Railway; in conjunction with the current Maintenance of Way Agreements
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Agreements, 1919-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: By-Laws of Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Employees' Hospital Association, 1952; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Revised July 1, 1952
  - Item 2: Code of Rules Governing the Condition Of, and Repairs To, Freight and Passenger Cars for the Interchange of Traffic, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Adopted by the Association of American Railroads, Operations and Maintenance Department, Mechanical Division. 1938 Revision. Supplement no.1
  - Item 3: Maintenance of Air Brake and Air Signal Equipment, 1953; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Association of American Railroads, Operations and Maintenance Department, Mechanical Division
  - Item 4: Agreement, 1938; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers, Roundhouse and Railway Shop Laborers, Establishing Rules and Working Conditions Governing Stationary Engineers and Firemen and Other Employees Herein Specified
  - Item 5: Union Shop Agreement, 1953; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Chesapeake District, and Employees Thereof represented by The Railway Labor Organization Signatory Thereto
  - Item 6: Vacation Agreement of December 17, 1941, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between certain Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers and their employees represented by the fourteen cooperating railroad labor organizations. Interpretations thereon. Award of Referee in connection therewith.
  - Item 7: Agreement, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between Pere Marquette Railway and Employees in the Maintenance of Way Department Covering Crossing Watchmen and Similar Positions represented by the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees
  - Item 8: Agreement, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and Its Train Dispatchers represented by the American Train Dispatchers' Association
  - Item 9: Agreement, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Maintenance of Way Employees. Represented by the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, covering Rates of Pay and Working Conditions
  - Item 10: Agreement, 1946; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Maintenance of Way Employees represented by the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, covering Rates of Pay and Working Conditions
  - Item 11: Agreement, 1919; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Director General of Railroads in respect of Railroads in Federal Operation and Employees thereon represented by the United Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees and Railway Shop Laborers
  - Item 12: Agreement, 1919; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the United States Railroad Administration and the Employees Represented by the Railway Employees Department of the American Federation of Labor and Its Affiliated Organizations of the Mechanical Section and Divisions Nos.1, 2, and 3 thereof.
  - Item 13: Agreement, 1973; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and All that Class of Clerical Office, Station and Stores Employees Represented by the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Agreements, 1914-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Rules and Rates of Pay for Trainmen, 1943; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, Operating Department. Rules effective September 1, 1927. Rates effective December 1, 1941. Reprinted March 1, 1943.
  - Item 2: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Train Dispatchers, 1926; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Chesapeake and Ohio Railway
  - Item 3: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Firemen and Hostlers, 1931; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Excluding Hocking Division)
  - Item 4: Rules Governing the Use of Motor Cars, Hand Cars, Push Cars, Trailer Cars and Velocipedes, 1954; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Southern Region
  - Item 5: Rules Governing the Use of Motor Cars, Hand Cars, Push Cars, Trailer Cars and Velocipedes, 1952; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Chesapeake District
  - Item 6: Rules Governing the Use of Motor, Push, and Trailer Cars, Velocipedes, and Other MofW On-Track Equipment, 1961; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 7: Rules for the Government of the Operating Department, 1925; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 8: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Engineers, Firemen and Hostlers, 1923; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 9: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Agents, Telegraphers, Telephone Operators, and Levermen, 1963; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 10: Safety Rules, 1932; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 11: Rules and Regulations and Rates of Pay Covering Maintenance of Way Employees, 1917; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company of Indiana
  - Item 12: Rules and Regulations and Rates of Pay Covering Maintenance of Way Employees, 1914; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 13: Rules and Instructions for Train Handling, 1966; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Chesapeake and Ohio Railway; Baltimore and Ohio Railroad
  - Item 14: Rules and Wage Schedule Governing Telegraphers, Telephoners, Levermen and The Exclusive Agents Specified, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Baltimore and Ohio Railroad
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Agreements, 1931-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Rates of Pay for Engineers, Firemen, Hostlers and Hostler Helpers (Including Hocking Division), 1944; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 2: Shop Crafts Agreement: Rules Governing Machinists, Boilermakers, Blacksmiths, Sheet Metal Workers, Electrical Workers, and Carmen. Apprentices and Helpers., 1969; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 3: Motor Car Rules, 1968; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 4: Safety Rules, 1950; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 5: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Agents, Telegraphers, Telephone Operators, and Levermen, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 6: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Firemen and Hostlers, 1932; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Hocking Division
  - Item 7: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Engineers, 1931; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 8: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Firemen, Hostlers and Outside Hostler Helpers, 1932; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 9: Shop Crafts Agreement: Rules Governing Machinists, Boilermakers, Blacksmiths, Sheet Metal Workers, Electrical Workers, and Carmen. Apprentices and Helpers., 1950; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 10: Schedule of Wages and General Regulations for Firemen and Hostlers, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Agreements, 1947-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Book of Rules, 1963; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 2: Agreement, 1960; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen. Rules effective September 1, 1927. Rates effective July 1, 1960.
  - Item 3: Agreement, 1963; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad and the employees represented by the Order of Railroad Telegraphers.
  - Item 4: Agreement, 1962; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and Yardmasters represented by Railroad Yardmasters of America. Governing the hours of service, working conditions and rates of pay for Yardmasters at the points specified
  - Item 5: Agreement, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters and the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, Governing the hours of service, working conditions and rates of pay for Yardmasters at the points specified
  - Item 6: Agreement, 1963; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, the Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad, and the Staten Island Rapid Transit Railway and the Order of Railroad Telegraphers
  - Item 7: Supplemental Agreement, 1959; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and the employees represented by the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, Concerning the Rearrangement of Track Forces
  - Item 8: Agreement, 1951; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and All that Class of Employees Herein Specified represented by the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, establishing Rules and Working Conditions
  - Item 9: Agreement, 1966; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad and All that Class of Employees Herein Specified represented by the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, Establishing Rules and Working Conditions
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Agreements, 1925-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Agreement, 1956; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Railway Patrolmen's International Union, AFL-CIO and the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, the Staten Island Rapid Transit Railway. Covering Rates, Rules and Working Conditions.
  - Item 2: Agreement, 1963; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad and the employees represented by the Order of Railroad Telegraphers
  - Item 3: Agreement, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and the employees of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Co. hereinafter specified, represented by United Transport Service Employees, Local 320
  - Item 4: Union Shop Agreement, 1951; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad, Staten Island Rapid Transit Railway and the employees represented by Non-Operating Organization Signatory Thereto
  - Item 5: Agreement, 1969; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad, Staten Island Rapid Transit Railway and All that Class of Clerks and Other Office and Station Employees represented by the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees
  - Item 6: Agreement, 1925; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and All that Class of Clerks and other Office and Station Employees represented by the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees
  - Item 7: Agreement, 1953; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and All that Class of Clerks and Other Office and Station Employees represented by the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees
  - Item 8: Agreement, 1973; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad, Staten Island Rapid Transit Railway and All that Class of Clerks, Transportation-communication and Other Office and Station Employees represented by the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees
  - Item 9: Book of Rules, 1951; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Item 10: Agreement, 1951; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Chesapeake District, and Its Foremen and Supervisors in the Maintenance of Equipment Department represented by the American Railway Supervisors Association
  - Item 11: Agreement, 1955; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Northern Region (excluding Hocking Division) and Foremen Employed in the Maintenance of Equipment Department represented by the Pere Marquette Supervisors' Association
  - Item 12: Agreement, 1951; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Chesapeake District) and the International Longshoremen's Association, Local 1768. Port of Toledo, Ohio
  - Item 13: Agreement, 1945; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Chesapeake District) and the International Longshoremen's Association, Local 158. Port of Toledo, Ohio
  - Item 14: Agreement, 1945; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Masters, Mates and Pilots and Unlicensed Employees represented by the National Organization, Masters, Mates and Pilots. Rules Governing Rates of Pay and Working Conditions. (2 copies)
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Agreements, 1940-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Rates of Pay of Employees covered by Agreement, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (as now constituted, not including Hocking Division) and the employees represented by the International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers, Roundhouse and Railway Shop Laborers
  - Item 2: Agreement, 1945; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Chesapeake District) and All that Class of Clerical, Office, Station and Store Employees represented by the Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees
  - Item 3: Agreement, 1957; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Chesapeake District) and Assistant General Yardmasters, Yardmasters, and Assistant Yardmasters represented by Railroad Yardmasters of North America
  - Item 4: Agreement, 1958; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Marine Engineers represented by Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association, no. 11, Hampton Roads Area, Rules Governing Rates of Pay and Working Conditions
  - Item 5: Agreement, 1924; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and all that class of employee represented by System Federation No. 41, Railway Employees Department, AFL, Mechanical Section No. 1 Thereof. Rules Governing Hours of Service and Working Conditions of Employees in the Maintenance of Way, Telegraph, Signal and Transportation Departments
  - Item 6: Agreement, 1957; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, Pere Marquette District, and Its Yardmasters represented by the Railroad Yardmasters of North America
  - Item 7: Agreement, 1959; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Tug Captains and Mates represented by National Organization, Masters, Mates and Pilots, Local 10, Hampton Roads Area, Rules Governing Rates of Pay and Working Conditions
  - Item 8: Agreement, 1953; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Chesapeake District, Hocking Division) and the employees represented by the International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers, Roundhouse and Railway Shop Laborers Establishing Rules and Working Conditions Governing Stationary Engineers and Firemen, Shop Laborers and Other Employees herein specified on the Hocking Division
  - Item 9: Agreement, 1955; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Southern Region and Hocking Division) and Train Porters represented by the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters, Rules Governing Rates of Pay and Working Conditions
  - Item 10: Agreement, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Yardmasters, and Assistant Yardmasters represented by Railroad Yardmasters of America